Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel. Amid Bitcoin
reaching new all-time highs and the
favorable treatment of the
cryptocurrency under the Trump
administration, there's been a rise in a
new type of company, the so-called
Bitcoin Treasury. Uh, businesses who opt
to hold Bitcoin on their balance sheet.
A strategy that was first popularized by
the eccentric CEO Michael Sailor and his
company Micro Strategy, now just called
Strategy, I guess, because it's grown so
much, which has been capturing a few
spotlights in 2025. You see, 5 years
ago, Micro Strategy was a business
intelligence company that was well off
of its uh.com heydays, experiencing
years of declining revenue and
compressing margins. But in August of
2020, the company became the first
publicly listed stock to buy Bitcoin, a
strategy that 5 years later has made
Strategy one of the largest 100
companies in the US. with the stock
having risen roughly 2600% over the past
5 years, nearly three times the return
of Bitcoin itself, something that has
been referred to as an infinite money
glitch. And as you'd expect from any
infinite money glitch, it hasn't taken
long for other companies to clamor into
the space. Uh some notable examples
include Tesla, Block, and GameStop, who
over the past few years have made
announcements around acquiring Bitcoin.
But the activity has really accelerated
recently with us now having over 166
publicly traded companies who own
Bitcoin. uh more than triple the amount
we had the previous year and these
companies collectively owning roughly 5%
of all outstanding Bitcoin. In fact, the
group has quickly become one of the
largest buyers of the cryptocurrency
with for the third quarter in a row
these companies actually buying more
Bitcoin than Bitcoin ETFs. But while
strategy has been praised by some uh in
particular Michael Sailor himself for
this feat of financial engineering, the
trend has been raising a couple of
eyebrows, especially given that a number
of these companies, strategy included,
actually trade for valuations that well
exceed the value of the Bitcoin these
companies hold. So why are investors
buying Bitcoin Treasury stocks? And is
it truly the infinite money glitch, the
Bitcoin prophecy being fulfilled as
foretold, or just a gimmick to cash in
on the crypto craze? Well, that
naturally depends on who you ask. And
today, I'll share the thesis around
paying $2 for $1 Bitcoin to highlight
why investors are arguing that this
might make sense as an investment, but
also the risks that it entails. But
let's start off with explaining how this
so-called infinite money glitch works.
Uh, a big component to this strategy is
the fact that strategy stock MSTR uh
trades at a premium to the value of the
Bitcoin that it holds. uh with this
known as MNAV or multiple of net asset
value and for strategy it's in the past
sat between two and three times meaning
the stock price has been two to three
times the diluted Bitcoin per share. Now
it's worth highlighting that strategy
does still operate its business
intelligence software business. Uh, so
that does also add value to the stock
here, but the business earns less than
$500 million in revenue annually
compared to the $75 billion it has of
Bitcoin. And the business actually loses
money at the operating income level. So
most people do view the company
primarily as a Bitcoin vehicle. And
because of the company's premium
valuation, it's been able to raise a
bunch of money by issuing new
securities. Uh, use that money to buy a
bunch of Bitcoin, which has arguably
helped to support the price of Bitcoin
and push it higher. uh which has allowed
Micro Strategy to issue more securities
given that now the asset it holds has
increased in value and allowing the
company to effectively rinse and repeat
with the company having tripled its
diluted share count since 2020. But it
brings us to the first confusing part of
the strategy. Why would investors buy
MSTR at a premium when they could just
take that money and buy more Bitcoin
themselves? After all, it's generally
not a good idea to pay $2 for $1 of
well, anything. And while some have
argued that strategy uses leverage here
and that helps to enhance the returns,
individuals could arguably themselves
borrow money to leverage Bitcoin and buy
more of it.
So why don't they? Well, at a very high
level, it's been argued online that the
stock's premium represents investor
enthusiasm for the space, confidence in
Sailor Strategy here, as well as the
view that the stock's premium will
actually continue to expand in the
future. And Michael Sailor himself has
indicated that the premium comes from
the company's credit amplification,
options advantage, passive flows, and
institutional access. Now, if none of
that made any sense to you, don't worry.
You aren't alone. Uh, now try to flesh
out the proposed reasons for the
valuation outside of just markets aren't
good at math. For one, there are some
places where borrowing money to buy
Bitcoin isn't really feasible at the
individual or even at the fund level. Uh
so this premium could in part reflect a
sort of regulatory premium given that
the uh investment is allowing investors
to get this exposure that's otherwise
hard to find in the space. There's also
the argument that Strategia here has,
you know, again, the intelligent
leverage, uh, which is more or less the
argument that the company's able to get
more attractive financing than
individuals could get themselves.
Because while the company has issued
roughly $30 billion in common equity
since it first started buying Bitcoin,
it's also borrowed an additional $9
billion by selling convertible notes and
$3 billion by selling preferred shares.
And it's how this leverage is structured
that's gotten a lot of attention from
investors. You see, leverage is a
two-edged sword. Yes, it does amplify
your return if the amount you earn on an
investment exceeds the cost of capital,
but if it doesn't, then it actually
amplifies your losses. So, the cost of
capital plays an important role in how
profitable leverage will end up being.
But in Strategy's case, they've been
able to raise debt at very low at times
0% interest rates for the purpose of
buying more Bitcoin by focusing instead
on those convertible notes. You see,
convertible notes are a type of hybrid
security that, as name implies, allows
the lender to at some point under
certain conditions convert the debt that
the company owes them into just equity
of the company, which is an attractive
feature for lenders since it gives their
debt more upside. If the stock happens
to skyrocket in value, even if they have
a high conversion price, which strategy
tends to have on its convertible notes,
they get that upside exposure to the
investment. And if it doesn't perform
well or even just stays flat, then they
get their money back plus any interest
they might have earned. And because
Strategy is such a volatile stock with a
beta of over three, that conversion
feature is quite valuable and has led to
these very low interest rates. Now,
naturally, these convertible notes don't
operate the same as typical debt, and
this doesn't represent typical leverage.
Uh, but you still effectively have these
convertible lenders uh giving more money
to the company and accepting fewer
shares, assuming conversion happens, for
the right to this convertability. And
the company benefits because they're
getting more bang for their buck from
their shares to benefit current
investors. As for the preferred shares
that strategy has issued, they do
function more closely to typical debt
and pay a higher dividend rate with only
one of the four classes being
convertible, but they still don't have a
severe impact on the company solveny
given that they still constitute equity
here. And skipping a dividend payment if
the company were say in a pinch wouldn't
constitute a default from the company.
Uh it would come with other consequences
which we'll touch on. Uh but it has been
argued that focusing on convertible
notes and preferred shares rather than
typical debt gives a company a better
ability to navigate volatile Bitcoin
prices without being forced to liquidate
its Bitcoin when it's in a pinch. Uh
whereas an individual investor, for
example, might get margin called if they
find that their investment has fallen.
And finally, there's the last sort of
key argument around the stock's premium.
uh the so-called Bitcoin yield, which
yes is a madeup term, which is something
investors love, but one that nonetheless
has been a focus for many investors of
Micro Strategy, with the company arguing
that it's been able to increase the
number of Bitcoin per share for its
investors over time with them presenting
a Bitcoin yield for 2024 of 74%. Now, of
course, the company isn't just magically
generating Bitcoin. There is someone
along the line who's paying for this
extra Bitcoin for shareholders here. So,
it is fairly misrepresentative to take a
company's number of bitcoins and divide
by the number of shares without
accounting for growing liabilities.
Nonetheless, it's argued that if
investors keep coming in and paying
higher conversion premiums and higher
valuations for the stock that it will
continue to be able to uh raise more
money, buy more bitcoin and increase the
bitcoin per share. So, those are some of
the key arguments you find online. Okay.
Now, Michael Sailor has also indicated
that because the stock has a sizable
options market and institutional
investors are trading the stock in part
due to its inclusion in some indices
that also helps. But there are plenty of
other publicly traded stocks with those
same sort of exposures that don't get
that same sort of multiple expansion
benefit. And there are other Bitcoin
treasuries with even higher multiples
that don't check those same boxes. So,
I'm not really sure how important those
market variables are. Nonetheless,
that's arguably why the company has been
able to succeed. And the skyrocketing
stock price has really made Sailor a
revered figure in the Bitcoin space with
a being a very vocal if not a bit
aggressive advocate for the
cryptocurrency.
>> People that use fiat currency as a store
of value. There's a name for them. We
call them poor. Okay.
>> So, even among real diehard Bitcoin
fans, the stocks managed to earn its
place as a portfolio diversifier,
I guess. And while you might still be
scratching your head trying to figure it
all out, other companies have heard
enough to uh start mimicking the model
themselves with some companies again
just adding Bitcoin to their balance
sheet to adopt it as one of their
capital allocation assets. While other
companies have completely pivoted away
from uh their perhaps loss-making
ventures to focus entirely on becoming a
Bitcoin focused entity with us also
seeing a rise of Bitcoin enthusiasts
buying out defunct public companies to
convert them into treasuries as well as
a revival of Bitcoin focused spaxs
because I'm sure it'll go better in the
cryptocurrency space with companies
recognizing that they can buy $1 of
Bitcoin and effectively sell it for $2
if they do so as a publicly traded
treasury company. It's easy to see why
the trend has picked up speed given that
a number of these companies have seen
their share price shoot up over 100% on
the announcements that they would be
buying Bitcoin despite there not being
any meaningful movement in Bitcoin's
price over those periods. Meaning the
company hasn't actually made any gain on
its investment yet. A phenomenon that
draws parallels with do companies in
2000 where companies would just add dot
to their name and see a jump in their
price or even the blockchain companies
of 2017. And the idea is quickly
spreading to other areas of the
cryptosphere as well with Ethereum
treasury companies also becoming a
popular concept and even Trump's own
World Liberty Financial recently
launching a publicly listed stock to
raise $1.5 billion for the purpose of
buying its own World Liberty Financial
token. Now, while some have been
highlighting the rise of Bitcoin
treasuries as evidence of Bitcoin's
adoption, naturally, this does blur the
line between companies that genuinely
believe in the future of cryptocurrency
as a store of value and companies that
are treating it as a gimmick to capture
investor enthusiasm and access to
capital markets. In London, for example,
most of the UK listed companies that
have announced Bitcoin treasuries are
small loss-making companies with small
trading volumes. In fact, we've even
seen some of the companies we've covered
on this channel for paying YouTubers to
promote their loss-making businesses as
promising investments now announcing
their own Bitcoin treasuries. So, the
strategy has seemingly become that if
your stock doesn't have a good business,
if you're losing money, you just
announce that you're buying Bitcoin and
investors will forgive you for not being
good at your job, at least for a little
bit. Now, having a bunch of companies
rush into the space to buy Bitcoin,
especially those with questionable
financials, does present a number of
challenges. While it does lead to more
institutions owning and controlling
Bitcoin, which I've been told now is a
good thing, it does also increase
competition for capital. If you have a
100 companies all offering the same sort
of Bitcoin exposure, there's going to be
more competition to attract investor
funds, which will require either higher
interest rates offered by these
companies or other sort of conversion
concessions that might not be to the
advantage of current investors. Even for
strategy, as the company grows, it will
likely struggle to maintain its Bitcoin
yield, as it will require exponentially
increasing the number of shares or
hybrid securities that it issues. And in
fact, we've already seen the company's
premium relative to its Bitcoin holdings
decrease over time with it more recently
trading at roughly 1.5 times, which
could prove challenging if your main
business model is selling shares. And in
fact, the company has issued guidance
that it won't issue more shares for the
company below a 2.5 times MNAV except to
pay off interest or dividends. Meaning
the company will only accept new
investors to help pay off the old ones.
Now, I know you're thinking this is
starting to sound a little bit
triangular, but that just means you're
thinking too hard about it. It also
again remains unclear whether we're
truly seeing that paradigm shift around
whether conventional companies will
treat Bitcoin more as a balance sheet
asset. And it could prove challenging
for more of these conventional companies
to adopt Bitcoin. If you suspend your
disbelief for a moment and operate under
the assumption that Bitcoin might not
always increase in value, it is a pretty
volatile asset for companies to be
parking their excess savings into. Yes,
the US dollar does typically lose value
over time, but if you are a profit
earning company with attractive return
on investment opportunities, you likely
won't want to invest your excess cash
that you might need in the near future
in these volatile assets. which is also
why you don't typically see companies
parking any sizable amount of their cash
into the stock market, but rather lower
risk bond and money market investments,
even though the stock market has over
time done very well. In fact, investors
may actually punish companies for doing
just that. It's quite common for holding
companies that just own other stocks to
actually trade at a discount to their
net asset value. It's also worth
highlighting that while strategy has
more or less become just a proxy for
leverage Bitcoin investing the
correlation between MSTR and Bitcoin
prices itself while positive has varied
quite a bit over time with on a monthly
basis the figure typically sitting
between 0.5 and8 and while expanding
multiples and issuing securities works
quite well when it works it also doesn't
when it doesn't. Naturally this leverage
gives these companies a lot of downside
exposure should Bitcoin's price
decrease. And while yes, strategy has
focused on these hybrid investments to
circumvent some of the main pain points
of leverage, it still presents risk. The
company may still need to sell Bitcoin
to make dividend payments, which will
hurt that supposed Bitcoin yield, which
will hurt their share. And if the
company skips a dividend payment, that
will greatly impact the valuation of
their securities, which will make it
difficult to continually raise more
money to meet dividend payments or to
buy more Bitcoin, which will eventually
require the company to sell its
holdings. And on the conversion dates,
there's a risk that if MSTR is not above
the conversion price, that the note
holders will require their money back
and force further Bitcoin liquidation,
which could actually impact the price of
Bitcoin and lead to this sort of
opposite effect of the infinite money
glitch. And as more questionable
companies pile into this strategy, that
just increases the risk of the exposure
here. Now, I will again highlight that
for strategy, they do have that hybrid
exposure, which is different from
typical leverage, and the convertible
notes and prefer only represent roughly
17.2% 2% of the company's Bitcoin value
on its balance sheet, meaning the
balance sheet is not actually that
excessively levered. It's also unclear
how levered in general the Bitcoin space
has become. However, strategy itself
does operate at a current ratio below
one times, meaning that does have more
current liabilities due in the next 12
months than it has current assets to
meet those liabilities, albeit they
might not all be cash liabilities. And
as more companies with questionable
financials enter the space, that only
increases the risk of a correction here.
a risk the company faces even if Bitcoin
remains flat with a stock having lost a
fifth of its value over the past month
despite Bitcoin not really moving that
much. Now truly none of this is to argue
that strategy or Bitcoin is going to
collapse in price. Uh trends like this
can continue for quite a long time. Uh
while we have seen bubbles in the past
in for example real estate, it does
typically require a sort of catalyst to
kick off the deflation of those asset
prices. And if demand for Bitcoin does
continue to increase if we do see more
institutional adoption, then this could
continue for quite some time. But is
interesting how departed this is from
the initial arguments for Bitcoin of not
your keys, not your coins, building a
system in protest of Wall Street and now
cheerleading their involvement.
Nonetheless, it's not Bitcoin's fault
that Michael Sailor is its number one
fan. And we'll have to wait and see how
things ultimately shake out. Anyway,
that's the video. Thanks for joining me
today. If you like this video, please do
make sure to like, subscribe, all that
good stuff. It does help the channel
tremendously. Let me know your thoughts
on the strategy strategy down below and
Bitcoin treasuries as a whole.